to a keep this church alive
six years ago, seven years ago, and b
continually breathe the life of Christ
into each and every one of us and this
body. So, I'm honored
to serve with you and walk alongside of
you and you have continually greatly
impacted my life. It's like every time
just was it th Friday we were standing
out back talking a little bit and I'm
just like this is exactly what I need to
hear. I wish Shnie was standing here
right now cuz she needs it too. So, uh,
no matter if we're working on something
together or sweating out back together
or just sitting in the office talking,
there is, uh, there's always just a Rama
word that's ministering to me and my
family and each and every one of you as
well as you encounter him. So, I'm
appreciative of you. Thank you, Pastor
John.
[applause]
>> The honor is all mine, honestly.
Amazing. many amazing people we have in
this church. So many of you guys are
just dearly, dearly loved by the Lord.
Just precious saints. I'm so honored to
walk with you all. Thank you for that
glowing uh announcement there. Yes.
Sorry. I uh I was thinking about the
word this morning and had like this last
minute thought and was like trying to
put it in there. But anyways,
well, we had a a great time last week.
It wasn't too hot. We didn't we didn't
overheat. Um at least I didn't. I don't
think Allan any anybody get the
opportunity to dunk Allan last week.
No, we let all the kids Oh, Matthew got
to dunk Allen. Then Judah did, too. Was
that fun? Good job. Good job.
>> Yeah, we Now you know where to send the
chiropractic bill.
Oh, well, praise God. Lord, we love you.
Thank you, Lord. Lord, as we worshiped
you this morning, it it's such a
wonderful thing to be in your presence,
Lord, to taste of of your spirit and to
be reminded, God, of your faithfulness
over the years, Lord. Um, we just bless
you. We we acknowledge, God, that you
are perfect, Jesus. You are perfect in
all of your ways.
>> Lord, there's there's none like you,
Lord. I I remember the day that I met
you and everything changed. And then I
remember as I discovered you, God, um
more and more through your word, I
discovered just perfect humanity.
So, we're grateful, God.
I'm grateful, Lord, for the way that you
have loved me back to health, for
investing in my life, for investing in
my future. And Lord, we just so adore
you and look forward to all that you're
going to do this morning. So, Holy
Spirit, come.
We welcome you. We just invite you to
rest on us and to open our hearts and
our minds and our eyes to see Jesus, to
see the father uh in in such a greater
light this morning. Amen.
>> Amen.
So,
I don't know about you guys, um, but
I've I've never I'm going to pick on
Liam Niss for a few minutes. [laughter]
It seems like a lot of the the movies
that he has done in the last decade or
so are are movies where uh his daughter
was brutally tortured or something and
and kidnapped and tortured and it's all
these vengeance type movies for a kid
being abducted or whatever. And um I was
thinking about that because it pertains
to what I feel like the Lord has us to
talk about today. But um when I was
growing in my faith and as a young man
and learning uh to cooperate with this
program with this uh transformational
process uh that the Lord is currently
still working on me, transforming me
into the image of Jesus. uh and the work
of the spirit, how many of you know will
sometimes surprise you at some of the
things that he highlights or some of the
things that he brings to the surface and
says, "Hey, this is the season we're
going to work on this. We're going to
redeem this." And and um I I I remember
as a young father, I really was aware of
um just the strong sense of justice that
I've always carried even when I wasn't
walking with the Lord.
And I was careful about things that I
consume, things that I would watch
because of the effect it would have of
what it stirred up inside of me. And so
I really strayed away from movies and
stories that had to do with kids being
abducted, you know, and and the dad then
going on this murderous rampage, uh,
which seems relatively justified in
light of the way that these horrible
stories. How many of you have read or
saw the movie The Shack?
So, guess what? I've never read it and I
never watched it. And that's why people
would say, "Oh, man. It's the best thing
ever. You need to like read The Shack."
And I was like, "Okay, I've heard people
describe what's going on with the
Shack." And I'm like, "That's not safe
for me to read something like that." Um,
and then I discovered that it was
fiction. Uh, it wasn't actually, no, was
it be science fiction? Yeah, it wasn't
actually true story. it was just
something that somebody made up. And I
said, "Why would you make that up?
Why talk about something like that if it
wasn't really a true story?" So,
anyways, that's my punch.
Um,
last, well, it wasn't last week. So, two
weeks ago, uh, how many of you were here
when I talked about getting a blood
transfusion
and a much healthier understanding of
the cross? a much healthier
understanding, biblical understanding,
uh, Jewishbased
perspective on this subject matter of
Jesus's blood
and how it saves us, how it heals us,
how it cleanses us.
Um, now I had made a statement or two in
that message that were a bit jolting for
folks that maybe the way that you were
raised in church uh, your your paradigm
as far as your understanding of why the
cross works. Why did why did the son of
god why did god incarnate have to come
and suffer
torture and bleed and die for me? And
how do I
reconcile that reality in my heart to
all of my sins being forgiven and
absorbed? Okay. So, if you weren't here
two weeks ago, I don't want to preach
that message again. Uh but I I made a
statement and I think I was quoting
Eaton Bar uh that the blood was never
about wrath. It was about
sanctification, about purification and
about life.
And so I I had also made a statement and
I've preached a few messages before
about how God's nature is not to punish
us. God is not a punisher. Not saying
that God does not discipline, but often
we mistake the discipline of God for
punishment. And so often our our
theology or our understanding of God is,
how many of you have ever heard it said
something like, "Well, God has no more
wrath because he poured it all out on
his son. He's got no more wrath to put
on you because all of his anger was
released onto Jesus." Absolutely.
>> I have too because I was I was raised uh
to understand that that's what's going
on in the gospel that when we sin and
the brokenness of the world uh has to
have some sort of resolution. It has to
be
uh repaired. It has to be fixed. It has
to be paid off. A a debt towards God is
owed and Jesus paid that debt for me.
And if you've been going to church here
for very long, we offer a different,
more biblical, more Hebraic uh
understanding of sacrifice and of
atonement. Atonement is the word for how
you close this gap between offense and
being made whole, being back in
relationship. Um, so anyways, God is a
punisher. So, I want to deal with I felt
like I had to circle back around because
one of the responses that I get quite
often is we deserve wrath. How can how
can you how can you overlook the wrath
of God in the Bible?
And so when we talk about the wrath of
God, especially if we've been raised in
a more fundamental background or you've
heard lots of preaching,
we immediately go back to the, "Oh,
thank God for Jesus because Jesus took
all the wrath of God."
In a way that is true, but I feel like
today is a day I want to talk about the
wrath of God. What what is wrath to
begin with?
So last week when I talked about God not
being a punisher, the blood of Jesus
that God the father did not torture
Jesus.
God didn't punish Jesus. Jesus wasn't
being punished. Jesus offered his life
as an offering to flush death out of our
system.
>> Because life was in the blood and blood
was used as a cleansing agent
in ancient Hebrew culture. They didn't
torture the animals.
sacrificial victims, animals in Jesus,
uh weren't satisfying an angry god by
him
feeling better because something
suffered. That that's not God at all.
That is not the God we serve.
So, we need to take a hard look at the
issue of wrath because I get asked
about, well, what about wrath? We
deserve wrath, don't we? And uh it's
it's it's
not one that I have found easy to have a
conversation about. So we're going to uh
dive in here. But before we talk about
wrath or God's wrath, I have a few
questions for us to consider.
And this is all in the context of us
becoming an emotionally healthy church.
Because part of our transformation into
the image of Jesus is dealing with all
of the hurt and the pain and really how
we react and respond to uh problems and
issues and hurtful things and offenses
in life. [clears throat]
So here's a few questions. Should we
justify violence of any kind?
How about in self-defense?
Can you justify doing violence? If
someone kicks in your door and they're
trying to murder your family, can you
justify doing violence to stop that act?
>> That's a good answer.
At at what scale could you consider
things to be violent? I I personally
don't like a cockroach in my house. I
will put an end to that life
immediately.
>> Yes. My my mother my mother used to like
oh don't kill it and pick up bugs and
put them outside, you know. I I I just
Yeah. Anyways,
against who or what and at what threat
level do we justify? Well, that is a
justified bit of violence.
How do we as Christians process our own
wrath?
I would like to say that everyone
experiences wrath.
Um,
I was thinking about it and wrath is
like this most visceral reaction to
death and evil. It's it's what happens
inside of us when something
very wrong happens to someone we love.
I remember when uh when COVID happened,
I I got a reputation um I think even
around the world, which is funny, but uh
through the catch the fire network of
being the co kid. It wasn't really the
reputation that I wanted. A lot a lot of
I know, right? A a lot of the um uh
catch the fire leaders are known for
their revival meetings. Uh you know, one
guy carries this gift of the spirit or
the other. They know me as the the co
kid. Uh because when the CO outbreak
happened, I think some of you guys may
remember um
lost some lost some folks, some uh
really good folks. And I remember
something inside of me when I when I
learned that Ivormectin
would knock it out
>> in like two days. Something something
visceral happened inside of me. I was I
was so
moved and upset. And it wasn't that I
was upset at anybody in particular. It
was that I I had this burning desire to
not let another person on my watch die.
And so some of you were recipients of
that, but I would look on Facebook if
somebody was going through the symptoms
that I was aware of because I had been
very sick with COVID. And uh thanking
the Lord that we found a doctor that
would prescribe hydroxychloricquin.
Got to say that right. uh because that
works too. It's um you know um
antiparasitic drugs would knock it out.
And um anyways, I'd get up at three
o'clock in the morning, drive across
town, you know, an hour away to take
people because I bought some Ivormectin
and uh
well, I wasn't planning on telling this
story, but I just remembered this is
just kind of cool. And whether you
believe it or not, it really happened. I
had bought a little bottle of
farm version
>> because at the boat dealership all the
fishermen were like hush hush or kind of
talking about the secret that they were
all getting healed of of COVID like that
and uh so I paid attention and I thought
oh my gosh because they had cattle and
stuff and I I thought this is this can't
be this can't be real but it was and so
we bought I went to the feed store or
had an employee go to the feed store and
buy a small bottle of ivormectin
uh liquid and found out the right dosage
and everything. And um I remember in the
first what two or three weeks the bottle
was half empty because it wasn't a very
big bottle. I mean it was like half the
size of a water bottle. Only takes a few
drops to heal you of COVID. And um I
remember thinking I've got to get more
like putting all my trust in this drug.
And the Lord said to me in my spirit he
said don't buy anymore. I don't want you
to buy anymore.
And I thought, "Oh, okay." And for the
next what, year and a half,
I think is how long that went on.
I don't know how many hundreds of people
came to my house. People I don't know,
neighbors of neighbors of people that I
knocking on my door and I'd set the
Ivormectin out. That bottle did not drop
until CO was almost over. And it was
still like until there was no more
threat of
>> CO
happened. It really happened. Now, like
I said, because that isn't super
glamorous and um they they uh the catch
the fire network people in other
countries and in Canada, they they did
not have the availability to get that
stuff. Um but I was able to connect them
with our doctor here is just across the
street and he was able to write
prescriptions to people on the other
side of the world. So people that were
dying like going to die. I know people
that died, they went into the hospital,
they never came out. It's true story.
It's horrible. It's just wrong. You
know, that disease is wrong. I don't
know who to blame for it, but there's
something inside of me still that is
just angry.
That's a that's a a righteous thing, a a
holy thing. It's a it's actually
how God is.
So, this
this word wrath in in the Old Testament,
I think we misunderstand. How many of
you when you think of the term wrath, we
think of the wrath of God. We think of
fire and brimstone. We think of God's
hand reached out ready to ready to
smite. We think about the destruction of
whole people groups, floods, hurricanes,
tornadoes, whatever. Well, technically
the word uh is like two letter. I think
it's PE um in Hebrew. Is that right,
Alan? And it just means like face, but
it's the implication is like the
countenance on someone's face. It's
like, you know, when you hear of
something of great evil, how your
countenance changes
and your nostrils flare that it it it
literally means like the flaring of the
nostrils. It's a it's an emotional
response
to evil. It's like um believe it or not,
I mean rodents aren't evil, but I have a
I have an emotional response to the
threat to my family of something that
could be carrying rabies running across
the floor.
I'm going to put that thing down. I will
stop at nothing to make sure that I
eliminate the threat to the family.
>> Amen.
Well, we don't like the idea of of
wrath. Uh when we think of God, we think
of God as being
this benevolent [sighs and gasps] teddy
bear of a dad. And it's not a bad way to
see him.
We like love. We like grace. We like
forgiveness because wrath sounds
dangerous and primitive and out of step
with God's character. But here's the
irony. We all experience wrath.
It's just a an emotional response to
evil. So, I want to talk about what do
we do with it? How how many of you when
you hear of stories of like human
trafficking?
What does that do inside of you? I
remember when people started talking
about it, the first time I heard of it
was like 2015,
14, 15 where churches were starting to
do something about it. And I was I was
clueless. I didn't know that was a
thing.
It's very inconvenient to think about
that there are people that are being
traded that are slaves today. How about
racism?
Have you ever witnessed somebody being
the on the wrong end of some racism?
Maybe you have been on the wrong end of
racism. Something
something inside of us is like that
ain't right. How about child abuse?
Child abuse for me as a one that was an
abused child even as a child I remember
being like this is not right. I knowing
that it was not right
you know ex extreme punishment for
trivial things. How about war?
We should get a pit in our stomach and
when we see people blowing each other to
smitherines absolute destruction of
people's lives.
betrayal. Maybe you've been betrayed.
That's probably a little more close to
home. If someone's ever betrayed you,
betrayed your trust, there's something
that rises up inside of you.
So the question is, how does love
manifest in our heart when those that we
love are harmed or threatened?
What do you feel?
Just being honest.
You're not indifferent.
Especially if you have kids or brothers
or sisters and maybe even your parents.
When something horrible happens to them,
something unjust,
you're not indifferent. You're not like,
"Oh, well, God will work it out in the
end."
Oh, you're angry, are we not?
>> And it's okay because love without anger
isn't actually love.
A father who never becomes angry when
someone's abusing their child really
doesn't love his kid very much, does he?
So, if we expect uh human love to oppose
evil, how much more would a perfectly
loving God oppose evil?
So, maybe wrath isn't an emotional
problem that God has. Maybe wrath is his
holy love confronting evil.
Matter of fact, I'd say this that God's
wrath is not the opposite of his love.
It's the expression of his love against
everything that destroys the people he
loves.
>> God's wrath is not the opposite of I'm
going to say it again, not the opposite
of love. It's the expression of his love
against everything that destroys the
people that he loves.
So
that was my intro.
When we talk about God's wrath, we need
to understand that God's wrath actually
flows out of love. It's not the opposite
of love. It's in opposition to the
things
that hurt his people because of love.
Exodus 32 through34 is an interesting
uh chunk of scripture.
Exodus 32 through34. You'll remember the
story. The children of Israel are
delivered from the Egyptians out of
slavery and they walk through the Red
Sea and all of their enemies are drowned
in the waters there.
They get on the other side and they camp
camp at Mount Si. And uh the Lord says,
"Get ready because I'm going to do
something special." This is the a God
that covenants with his people, that has
married his people, that has chosen to
be their God exclusively, and they will
be his people exclusively.
And Moses, he's called forward to lead
them through the wilderness into the
promised land. His his heart's desire is
always, I am taking you to a place where
you will be incredibly blessed, where
you have more than enough. We have
everything you need, where you can
exercise and live out this culture of
living with me in peace. Only you need
to become like me. And so he gives Moses
the commandments and Moses goes up on
the mountain and while he's etching out
or actually the finger of God is etching
out in stone uh the Ten Commandments or
the charter so to speak of their
covenant.
the the children of Israel get uh
I don't know if it was bored or if they
get uh antsy or whatever, but they're
like, "Where's this Moses guy that's
supposed to lead us?" Impatient, maybe a
right word. Impatient, where's he at?
Aaron, we want to worship Yahweh who led
us out of slavery. Make make gods for us
so that we can worship him. They they
want to get the show on the road.
They want to get this thing wrapped up.
And you know the story. Uh
Aaron says that well take all the
earrings and stuff off and he threw it
in the fire and out came a a calf.
>> Just rolled right out of just jumped
right out of the fire
according to Aaron. You know that was
his story.
So, while Moses is up there getting the
the words
from heaven straight from the finger of
God and spending time with Yahweh face
to face, uh talking about the the this
amazing covenant that he's going to make
is having embraced these people through
love and marrying these people. Well,
they were down there doing the opposite,
breaking the whole thing up. So, of
course, Moses comes down and smashes the
covenant. and but through Exodus 32
through34, if you'll remember,
God's visceral reaction to what was
going on there um was was wrath, right?
He was angry. He was mad. I don't know
about you, but if you just married
somebody and uh you know, you had to go
on a a I don't know, extended work
weekend or something and and you come
back and they're partying with somebody
else, I mean, you probably experience
something very close to what I'm talking
about. This visceral reaction inside to
I'm I'm offended, like deeply offended.
But if you'll remember,
God
We can we get into Exodus 34 and we are
privy to and I I love that God is an
emotional God and he's not afraid to
share that. And I think it's incredible
that the way that the book is written is
that God kind of discloses himself and
he's not hiding the fact that he's
having this discussion about how he
feels. He's this is just how he feels.
I'm ready to just wipe them all out.
I'll tell you what, Moses. Let's just
start over with you. I'll just start
over with you. We'll just get this thing
over with. And And Moses hits his knees
and he says, "Please don't do that.
Please don't do that. Remember the
fathers. Remember your promises.
Remember what is Egypt going to think.
Remember your loving kindness, oh God?"
He appeals to a different side. He
appeals to his love. It was the actual
love of God that was angry
because of love.
Anyways, and the Lord then rather than
giving them up because he was about to
blow up this covenant and say, "All
right, no more covenant."
But he does not. What does the Lord do?
He says, "Okay, I'm going to I tell you
what, I'm going to go with you.
Actually, there's a little back and
forth. I'm going to send my angel. I'm
going to stay back a little bit because
if they do this again, it it could get
ugly. I mean, I could Y'all realize
that, right? Like the Lord like loved
them enough to say, "But we need to put
some distance because they do that again
and this could get ugly."
And Moses, that's that's where Moses
says, "No, look, I don't want to go if
you won't go with me. You say that you
chose me. You say that you know me. You
say that you handpicked me, that you're
going to deliver me. I don't even I
don't even know what you look like.
Show me your face. Lord's like, "Oh, you
don't want to see this face. I I can't
show you my face. You can't live if you
see my face." There's something so
expressive about the face of God that
it's probably a good thing that we
haven't seen his face other than the
face of Jesus.
He says, "But I'll tell you what I'll
do. I'll walk by you and all my goodness
will go by you and you'll see who I
really am." And this is this is where he
reveals who he really is here in Exodus
34. Read it with me. Now the Lord
descended in a cloud and stood with him
there and proclaimed the name of the
Lord. And the Lord passed before him and
proclaimed, "The Lord, the Lord God,
merciful and gracious, long-suffering
and abounding in goodness and truth,
keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving
iniquity and transgression and sin, by
no means clearing the guilty."
You know what was so upsetting to the
Lord was that they created a god and
called it Yahweh.
That they fashioned
an image.
It wasn't that they thought they were
worshiping another god. Is that they
chose to decide how to worship him and
what he was going to look like.
Over and over and over again. The
problem that God had when he'd say
they've played the harlot. Y'all ever
read that in the Old Testament? How did
they do that?
Worshiping some other god. It's
character assassination.
He did not want to be associated with.
And it wasn't about like fingers and
toes and eyes and horns and things like
that.
It was about his character and his
nature.
Him setting the record straight here is
to say you got to understand who I am. I
am not like the other gods
as if they were even gods
as we know they are rebellious Elohim,
rebellious
spirit beings that people worshiped as
gods. But they as being the gods of the
other nations would do things like
demand blood.
They were the ones that got angry that
their people were associated with fear.
If they did something wrong, then the
God would retaliate.
Yahweh did not want to be associated in
that way at all. And yet at the same
time, he experiences anger
and he does something about it. He will
by no means
clear the guilty. You're like, "Well,
that doesn't sound great. that that
still has an awful ring to it. Well,
let's take a look.
According to this passage of scripture,
God introduces himself as compassionate,
gracious,
slow to anger,
and abounding in steadfast love.
Hallelujah.
>> It's not that he doesn't get angry or
experience the emotion of anger. It's
just what does he do with it?
We know that he's perfectly righteous
and that he could in his own right and
he's sovereign and holy and all that
stuff. He could do whatever he wants to.
But because he's a god of love, he does
the right stuff with his anger. So wrath
isn't God's first instinct. Love is. His
anger is slow. His mercy is abundant.
And his justice is absolutely necessary
for him to do something about it. He
can't just do nothing
and let it let it go by.
So I I don't know how how many of you uh
know who or love Tim Mackey know who he
is.
>> Couple of you. Tim Tim Mackey um he's a
a great theologian scholar of our day
and also a prolific Bible teacher and he
has um a um
I don't know if it's a program what to
call it but anyways he he he he started
what they call Bible project. Who knows
what Bible project is? Bible project is
fantastic where they tell the story of
the Bible and themes in the Bible
through uh illustrations as they unpack
it super simple taking very complex
truth and making it simple.
Uh anyways the Tim Mackey's perspective
is this that throughout scripture wrath
is often portrayed as God allowing
humanity to experience the natural
consequences of rejecting his life.
This is a better way of understanding
this. I even think that when I was
discipled, this is the way that
John Collins taught us.
Um, I'm going to say that again.
Throughout scripture, and and as we talk
more about it, you'll recall that this
is true. Wrath is often portrayed as God
allowing humanity to experience the
natural consequences of rejecting his
life.
If you think about Kings and Chronicles
and even 1 and 2 Samuel, that whole
history of Israel and its heyday and
also in its uh constant crisis,
every everything kind of revolved around
that. They would choose to intermar. And
it wasn't that intermarriage was wrong
in itself. It was that other nations
that were surrounding them belong to
they were married to these other gods.
And so when they would take another
family in, they would have to then
worship their gods. And by virtue, that
would be like spiritual adultery.
And all of the things that they
practiced because the other gods were
very
I don't I don't know the right words,
but they were just awful and had a lot
of awful ways in which they practiced
sacrificing children. Um, you know,
unfaithfulness to spouses, that was out
the window. uh lots of ways that they
practiced
or worshiped their gods that were very
unhealthy for humanity, unhealthy for a
culture where God's spirit was to dwell.
You we see this in the New Testament in
Romans. This is interesting. It's
probably
I don't know in our culture today,
Romans 1, it's like we let's start
somewhere around Romans 3. you know, we
don't like to to look at Romans 1, but
it's in there. We're talking about the
wrath of God. Romans 1's got the the
language of wrath in it.
Uh, so read it with me starting verse
18. For the wrath of God is revealed.
It's revealed from heaven. So Paul is
going to tell us what the wrath of God
looks like.
For the wrath of God is revealed from
heaven against all ungodliness and
unrighteousness of men who suppress the
truth in unrighteousness
because what may be known of God is
manifest in them. For God has shown it
to them.
And you guys probably know the rest. It
starts talking about worshiping the uh
creation instead of the creator. And
specifically this is talking about
sexuality, believe it or not. uh and how
we steward or how historically people
have stewarded their bodies.
If we jump down to verse 24,
I just want to point out, read it with
me. Therefore,
God also gave them up to uncleanness in
the lust of their hearts to dishonor
their bodies among themselves, who
exchanged the truth of God for the lie,
and worshiped and served the creature
rather than the creator who is blessed
forever. Amen. For this reason, God gave
them up to vile passions.
So in verse 18, it says, "The wrath of
God is revealed from heaven against all
ungodliness and unrighteousness of men."
And here's the definition is that his
wrath looks like
giving us over to our own ways.
Romans 1 repeats this cycle like God
gave them over.
So sometimes or I would say that most
often the wrath of God doesn't look like
fire and brimstone or lightning bolts,
but it's actually God saying, "If this
is what you insist on, I'm going to let
you have it." Sin eventually becomes its
own punishment.
I know. I wish I didn't know, but I do
know.
There's nothing worse than that feeling
when um and God is slow to anger, rich
in mercy, abundant in mercy,
longsuffering towards us. And it is
amazing to me how long he'll let us go
before he says, "Hey, look, you really
want that? Then I'll just let you have
it."
because the fruit of that is going to
eat you alive. So most of when you're
reading the prophets in the Old
Testament, if you understand that that's
what's going on, it makes it so much
more clear that it's this constant,
especially like Isaiah and Jeremiah,
it's this it's this constant plea
through the prophet to the people of
Israel, return to me, return to me,
return to me. If you not not do not
return to me, it's going to get ugly
because
you are going to reap what you sow. it's
going to come back on you. And it's not
like God is up there pulling the strings
making that happen. No, he's already set
things in motion. Rather, instead, God
is holding back,
always holding back
things from getting to us. The last
thing we want to do is have him remove
his hand and say, "If you insist, then
have it already."
But you'll recall the pattern in
scripture is that then he brings him
back once they've had a good taste of it
and they cry out to him. Brings him
back. Brings him back. Brings him back.
I'm so thankful that that is the nature
and character of our God.
>> Have you ever had a belly full of your
own folly?
>> Absolutely.
>> Where you're like, I can this is
horrible.
>> This is punishment. This is hell.
Wrath is God giving humanity what it
chooses. Romans 1. So Paul doesn't
describe
wrath primarily as fire. He describes it
as disintegration.
Notice the pattern. If we had read that
whole passage,
people reject God. God gives them over.
Life unravels.
Relationships fracture,
communities collapse,
hearts harden.
If you think about it, this echoes the
exile story, as I brought up. It's like
most of that promised land forward
in the Old Testament is is that story
over and over again, especially the one
to Babylon.
Humanity chooses life apart from God.
God honors that decision.
I had um yeah, I found that out
firsthand. I I grew up in a Christian
home and knew all the Christian stuff
basically, but not like heart didn't
really know it with my heart. I just
knew details that I'd heard
and uh went through a horrible season
with uh my parents divorce and
everything coming off the wheels. You
guys know I've talked about it. Uh, but
I remember when I hardened my heart and
I decided to just go crazy and do lots
of things that were um just dangerous,
harmful to myself, harmful to others,
harmful to God, hurtful to God, I should
say. And I remember having a having a
dream once and um I've never even talked
about this before, but the the dream was
this that like I was in heaven already
and angels that had their faces covered
wouldn't even look at me like open the
gates
and then I freefeld and I was free
falling to the earth and as I got closer
I just heard all this yelling and like a
mosh pit just ah a and all these hands
and I just fell right into the chaos and
uh I thought well that was a bit extreme
but that's how
either that was the Lord speaking to me
or me processing what was going on
because I did I I u just walked away
from church I walked away from uh really
anybody that loved me and just decided
to go crazy for a while and um I can say
that the Lord at some point stopped
protecting me from my own decisions.
They let me start feeling that weight of
decisions I was making. And um that got
my attention immediately.
That got my attention immediately.
Sitting in a jail cell. I was like
for writing in wet concrete [laughter]
of all things. Writing in wet concrete.
Went to jail for that.
had my attention.
So Anti Wright's perspective is this
about Romans 1.
Anti Wright, as you know, we talk about
him a lot and his perspectives, but he
he's saying that Romans is Paul is
retelling Israel's story. And I love
that. Uh, of course, that's kind of a a
higher learning position to take as you
begin to study at another level. Paul is
actually retelling Israel's story. And
wrath is covenantal language. So if
if you were not in covenant with God,
I'm not saying that wrath doesn't exist,
but it's not the same thing. This is
something that lovers would experience,
and it is the consequence of idolatry.
And throughout Israel's history, God
allows idols
and their archons and the powers that
are behind those idols to become
tyrants.
Sin enslaves.
Wrath exposes that slavery.
God's judgment isn't arbitrary.
It's the moral fabric of creation
responding to rebellion.
Deep thoughts. Deep thoughts.
All right, second point. So God wrath is
God giving humanity what it chooses. And
the second point is that God does not
delight in wrath. That like there's
nothing about it
that God likes.
Ezekiel 18:23.
Um,
do we have that one?
Maybe I didn't make a slide for Ezekiel
18:23,
but it says this. Do I have any pleasure
at all in that the wicked should die,
says the Lord God, and not that he
should turn from his ways and live?
That that chapter there in Ezekiel 18,
it's like God reasoning with Israel like
you say I'm unjust, but you're the one
that's actually unjust.
like I I'm I have no desire for anybody
to die, not even wicked people. I desire
that wicked people would turn and he
starts talking about if the wicked would
turn and amend their ways, then I will
absolutely embrace them and heal them
and bless them. And conversely, if
righteous people decide to then do
wickedness, they will suffer the
consequences of it. But that's not
because God enjoys that. He doesn't like
that at all.
He is the most long-suffering
person that you could ever imagine.
I mean, I've I've tried to really I've
tried to think about the heart of God,
what it must be like for him to actually
bear because he doesn't just blow it off
like, "Oh, well, you know, oh, yep,
Jesus, I did that to him. Okay, we're
good." No, the heart of God is grieved
over our pain. It's grieved over our
evil.
He's grieved over our tragedies.
Verse 32, you jump down. He says, 'For I
have no I have no pleasure in the death
of one who dies, says the Lord God.
Therefore, turn and live.
God's desire is always restoration.
>> Amen.
>> Huh?
>> Every warning in scripture is an
invitation.
I I remember um shortly after I received
Christ
when the Lord dealt with my own like
anger issue. Like I didn't
I didn't realize that it was what it was
until I had the Holy Spirit.
But for a couple years there, I I could
get super angry. I I don't know if
anybody has ever had this or maybe
you've heard me talk about this or not,
but I I remember getting super angry and
I got in a bunch of fights, too. And I
got chip teeth. Chip teeth to prove it.
But um
I remember when I would when I would get
angry, I could relate to The Incredible
Hulk because something would come over
me that was almost superhuman. And
adrenaline's probably got something to
do with that. But um
you know, I'd have a fight and and then
when I'd come down the next day
physically I would be sick
like and I didn't really pick up on that
until after I had received Jesus and
everything was great and I got in a
fight with my brother and that happened
to me. The Rage Monster came out and I
was like, "Whoa,
that is not from God."
I was like, "This is not God at all."
And and I remember telling the Lord
like, he did so much when he when he
remember I told you two weeks ago about
the transfusion of life where the blood
of Jesus actually purged me and cleansed
me and healed me in so many ways. But I
had to discover that, oh no, there's
lots more that God's going to work on.
And anger was like one of the one of the
or rage is a better way is one of the
first things that that he dealt with.
And uh I remember that sick horrible
feeling like like down in my bones and
my whole body hurt like the Hulk, you
know, when uh Dr. Banner would come back
to himself and he's like, "Oh, needs he
needs to be refreshed."
Um I remember telling the Lord, "I never
ever ever want to do this again. God,
would you please take this from me?" And
he did right then and there. I have
never never experienced that again. The
the rage monster. You know, I have had
some anger, but not like that. Does
anybody know what I'm talking about?
>> Absolutely.
>> Ever experienced go some guys are like a
few of you ladies, but uh yeah, I mean
if if you struggle with that, I can just
tell you right now, you you can totally
be delivered to that.
>> Yeah.
Anyways, uh Merislav Wolf, I I I love
this guy. He's um
one of the theologians that really
shifted and changed my life. But his
work exclusion and embrace, he talks
about um
reconciliation, forgiveness. He talks
about justice a lot. And he definitely
talks about h how do we process this
victim being left hanging? Um subject
matter. What what about the wrath of
God? What about vengeance is mine, says
the Lord. I will repay.
But here's here's Miris Vulfe. He says,
"Many modern people reject divine wrath
because they've never experienced
large-scale injustice." And um
he comes from uh Croatia, I think, where
the ethnic cleansing was going on with
his family. A lot of his family members
were um yeah, I won't even talk about
it, but experienced that ethnic
cleansing.
He said, "Victims know better.
If God never judges evil, then evil
wins. God has to do something about it.
He's not going to just say, "Oh, it's
okay."
Forgiveness without justice becomes
indifference.
And I'm I'm thankful to know that that's
not what God requires when he asks us to
forgive. It's not no big deal. I've been
violated. No big deal. God's going to
fix it.
The cross allows justice and mercy to
meet.
God refuses to ignore evil
because he overcomes it.
>> What's that?
The cross allows justice and mercy to
meet.
God refuses to ignore evil
because he overcomes it.
I I've talked about a story as I was I
actually I opened with this. I just
didn't talk much about it. But um as I
was growing in my relationship with the
Lord, probably four or five years in,
I started having these dreams of um
I wake up from the dreams and think,
"Oh, Jesus, I've been working so hard to
be holy and to be nice to people." And
I'm scaring myself with these dreams. Is
this a is this a sign that I'm really
like crazy or something or I'm I'm
really dangerous person? because I was
having these dreams where there would be
some perpetrator breaking into my house
or coming after my kids and my family
and I would do violence to this
perpetrator. And the problem was the the
biggest tension wasn't me doing the
violence necessarily. It was then, uhoh,
I have a corpse on my hands. What am I
going to do with this evidence that I
had done violence
even though it was justified? They were
hurting my family. And so that was
always the thing like throw them in a
ditch, throw them in a dumpster, you
know. And I really I thought I I
Lord have mercy. I'm damaged goods. God,
please tell me I'm not going to do
something like that, Lord. And uh I
remember going to my pastor and I told
my pastor about it and said I I got the
courage to actually say it out loud and
tell him. And he's like, "Oh no, that's
not what that means at all." He says,
"You know, you're experiencing somewhere
in your life a uh darned if you do, darn
if you don't situation. You're stuck.
You're trapped. You feel like if you you
you're experiencing some injustice
somewhere, and you feel like if you do
something about it, you'll be punished.
And I instantly was like, "Oh my gosh, I
was getting messed around at work." And
I'm the Christian guy. And I didn't want
to cause a scene or make a stir. But
basically, there was some inequality
going on. And I went and told the boss
said, "Hey, you can't do that. I've been
here longer. Why are you giving this guy
uh all this preferential treatment? Why
don't you just treat us equal? That's
not right."
And he said, "Okay." and that was it.
And I never had another dream.
Now today, I'm I'm seeing a much deeper
reality that God was at work in me to
really change my foundation and the way
I think about this visceral visceral
reaction that I have to injustice and
stuff that is wrong.
And the reaction that is appropriate is
to honoringly
challenge
that injustice
to say something to do something. Not
just to oh well doesn't matter or not to
do something crazy and decide to
be passive aggressive towards the people
that are responsible but rather to
address it. And that is a really really
healthy approach for us to understand.
Ultimately, God will
make everything right. God will judge.
There is such a thing as the judgment
seat of Christ. But how many of you know
that
we don't have to fear that?
I'm thinking of like 1 John 4
there where it talks about uh there is
no fear in love. Perfect love casts out
fear. Why? Because fear involves
punishment.
God is not a punisher.
He's he he's not looking to pay back
somebody.
No. When God expresses wrath, it's
actually his love
reaching out to stop
things from destroying his people, from
destroying those he loves.
How we doing?
>> Jesus doesn't sing save us from an angry
father. And we kind of covered this two
weeks ago, but we need to understand
that Jesus isn't standing there holding
dad back because dad's really angry at
something that you did.
This is some of that eaten bar
perspective.
Instead,
what do we see in scripture? God himself
bears wrath.
You can look at John chapter 3,
Romans 5,
Isaiah 53.
The father isn't against the son.
Father, son, and holy spirit, they all
together are rescuing humanity.
The cross reveals that God absorbs evil
rather than simply inflicting
punishment.
Jesus steps into the consequences of
human rebellion.
The judge becomes the judged.
Love pays the cost.
I think about
John chapter 3. Right there at the end,
there's a statement that says that those
that have not believed on him, the wrath
of God abides on them. That's a hard one
to
process, is it not? I mean, in my
evangelical American Christian
worldview, it'd be easy for me to walk
outside and think, heathens, wrath of
God abides on you.
Wrath's coming. You're going to suffer
the wrath of Almighty God. How about
Revelation
where the angel puts a sickle in and
reaps a harvest and then tramples the
the wine press of the wrath of God.
Oh my goodness.
I think that a lot of a lot of those
verses,
Paul's perspective
would have been understood and well
known as
nations being conquered by other nations
and the devastation that happens when
a a nation that has gone a muck because
they can't get along, right?
When when there's no unifi unity, a
house divided cannot stand. This is
happens nationally when when nations and
I Lord bless America. Please help us to
love one another and be unified again
>> because when a people group are divided,
they they just run a muck and they run a
mess and they're weakened. And it's
pretty well understood that because of
all that selfishness, because that's
what causes that, I I'm right. No,
you're wrong. I'm right.
because of all that selfishness, it just
makes you like pray for some stronger
nation that sees the resources that
you're sitting on and wants to come take
them. So when Paul often and even in the
New Testament when they're referring to
wrath like that,
it's that there's a day of reckoning
coming, it's it's framed within this
idea of
a day of the Lord or a day of wrath is
when everything switches over. when you
finally get nationally the repercussions
of not being able to work it out
together, of not being strong enough to
hold it together as a nation.
That's the way that I've seen wrath used
that way.
How many of you know that humanity in
general because of our inability to
unify because of our decisions and our
attitude of well no I know better.
I want to do it my way.
And what fixes that is our ability to
surrender to God and say, "God, I I have
no idea. My way is terrible. I I just
publicly acknowledge that right now."
Like my my way without the Lord is
terrible. I'm my own worst enemy.
I will absolutely make a mess out of
this deal.
Have sometimes do still
humanity as a whole in that attitude
towards God. No thanks. That Romans 1
was talking about no thanks. We've got
it all figured out. They became wise in
their own eyes.
decided how it's going to be in that
inability because when you're doing that
and everybody's doing that, nobody's
unified. Nobody's got anything to. If we
have any unity, it's all it's because
well, what you've got to offer serves my
purpose.
That's why when we believe in Jesus in
the person of Jesus and he comes to give
his life away and we understand that in
giving ourselves away and being in
covenant with one another and with God
that that brings life and health and
unity that cannot be broken. That's why
wrath is not for you. And we could say
that wrath in that sense is for those
that have not received Jesus. Does that
make sense? Is that slightly different
than the way that I proposed or the way
that you grew up with evangelical
American Christianity?
It's not just a decision. Oh, okay.
Well, I said the prayer and culturally I
go to church sometimes and I say, "Yep,
I believe in Jesus. Therefore, the wrath
of God does not abide on me.
because
Jesus took all the wrath from God.
No, it looks more like
I have received Christ. He's breathed
the spirit of life into my lungs. I've
become one with him and everything about
his life has been inherited.
I've surrendered my desire and my will
to do everything the way I want. And now
I'm living for this great plan that he's
laid out.
Wrath is not the final goal. How many of
you know that this plan that God has at
work is not just to wipe everything out?
Revelation 21 ends with no tears,
no death, no curse,
no mourning,
no evil.
God's final word is not wrath.
It's new creation.
It's a promise of a whole new world that
he's creating even now in you and
through you and for you.
Wrath clears the way.
I'm sorry. Wrath clears away evil so
love can flourish forever.
All right, I'm wrapping up.
Tim Mackey's perspective
is that the Bible begins in a garden and
it ends in a city. The whole story is
moving toward this renewed creation.
Wrath removes everything that corrupts
God's good world because love is your
destination.
So when we talk about the gospel, the
invitation,
all the warnings being an invitation,
it's not escape hell, it's come home.
Turn from the idols that are destroying
you.
Receive the God who loves you enough to
oppose everything that's killing you and
ruining your life.
Repentance isn't punishment. It's a
rescue.
Matthew.
Matthew in here.
So, here's a few questions
for us to answer as we're wrapping up.
Where am I resisting God's loving rule?
Where am I still
content to make my own decisions and
think that my way is better.
What would it look like if I could let
go of that?
Do I trust that he's good enough
to direct my steps,
rewrite my story?
Are there any consequences in my life?
Repercussions of my decisions that
I'm just calling bad luck or
the enemy that may actually be the Lord
just letting you have what you chose.
That's actually just an invitation to
come back to his heart.
I remember when I came back to the Lord,
I tried a couple times to do it on my
own to give up a few things
and the Lord said, "No,
I want all of you. I don't just want
part of you. I want all of you."
It's like with Lauren. I want all of
her.
I want to be her husband on Tuesday and
Wednesday. I want to be her husband
every day of the week.
God wants all of us.
We can trust him with all of us.
The last question is, am I
representing him well? Am I [snorts]
reflecting his heart?
Have I learned how to hate evil without
hating people?
>> Can I uh oppose injustice while loving
my enemies?
That's what he wants to do in his
church.
Only the spirit of God living inside of
us.
The nature of Christ being developed in
us could do this stuff.
>> Only a surrender to him [snorts]
produces that kind of a life.
[snorts]
Just imagine this. Imagine
the world with [snorts] no abuse,
no violence,
no addiction,
no death,
no corruption,
no guilt, no shame,
no burden.
[snorts]
We all long for this world.
This is what's been promised to us.
The only way God brings it about is by
finally dealing with evil.
That's wrath.
Not love's opposite,
but love's refusal to surrender.
>> [snorts]
[sighs]
>> Let's take communion
as we close. Let's take communion.
Probably should have had us do that
already, but let's go. Let's go for it.
Have a couple of our
leader service.
>> [snorts]
>> Thank you.
[snorts]
Aren't you grateful that God gave us
just a prophetic enactment, a tactile
way for us to
[sighs] step back into covenant to renew
and refresh,
rehearse
the covenant Jesus made with us.
Not just to remember, but
to kind of re-mbod.
This this is this moment is for you,
church. It's for us together, but it's
for you,
Lord. Thank you for what you've done,
Lord. We thank you for coming and
exhibiting perfect righteousness,
perfect love.
Lord, I thank you that you didn't just
do it like Superman. You did it
in human frailty.
Flesh and blood and bone just like us,
God.
Lord, I thank you that you are an
emotional God. that you feel everything
that we feel. Lord, there isn't anything
that we've experienced no
pain, no trauma,
no discouragement,
even anger that we don't that we feel.
[snorts]
You are intimately acquainted with our
grief.
Lord, we thank you for taking all of
that
upon yourself,
bearing our guilt and our shame, our
sicknesses and our diseases, God,
putting it to death, Lord.
Thank you. We just received your body.
Take the bread with me.
[snorts]
Today, as we share this cup,
as I spoke a few weeks ago about a
transfusion of life, I want you to
understand
that the very life of God, the life of
Jesus
is for you
to heal you, to cleanse you, to purify
you,
to cleanse even your conscience,
to make you whole.
Even the smell of smoke, the
remains of trauma and death, all of that
is dealt with in the blood of Jesus. So
Jesus, we thank you for your life.
Lord, we gladly accept your life.
We are your people. We are your hands
and feet. Take the cup with me.
So, if you've been watching online, God
bless you.
Pray you have a wonderful week. You
guys, if we can stand with you in
prayer, pray for you to all. If if God's
at work in your life, I would be so
excited to hear about it. If this if
you've had a a visual reaction to this
sermon,
please feel free. I' I would genuinely
love to
counsel you to to talk about it. I' I'd
like to know.
God bless you guys. Have a great week.